SaskiaHiltemann

Post-Doctoral Researcher, Bioinformatics & Education



About

De Carpentierstraat 24 2595HL, Den Haag The Netherlands

> saskiahilltemann @gmail.com

shiltemann O y in

ORCID: 0000-0003-3803-468X

Languages

Bilingual Dutch/English German & French

Skills

Python, C, C++, UNIX, Galaxy, Docker, Jekyll, LaTeX

Interests

Bioinformatics, Education & Training, Open Science, FAIR principles, Community Building, Genome Sequencing, Data Analysis, Workflows, Automation, Visualisation, Best Practices, Cancer Research, Microbiome Analysis, Infosec, CTF, Traveling, Hiking, Reading, Puzzles.

Education

Since 2021 **Post-doctoral Researcher** Erasmus Medical Center Focus on Microbiology Research, Federated Data Analysis, FAIR principles,

Open Science, Software Development and Bioinformatics Education.

2012-2020 Ph.D. Researcher, Bioinformatician Erasmus Medical Center

Focus on cancer analysis, metagenomics research. Galaxy tool and training

development.

2008–2010 M.Sc. LIACS, University of Leiden & TU Delft

Computer Science

Specialization in Bioinformatics

2005–2008 B.Sc. LIACS, University of Leiden

Computer Science

2002–2005 **B.Sc. course work** University of Leiden

Physics & Astronomy

2002 **High School (VWO)** Alfrink College, Zoetermeer

Specialization in Science & Technology

Work Experience

Current Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam

Post-doctoral Researcher & Bioinformatician

- Training, Outreach & Dissemination
- · Federated Data Analysis Infrastructure Development
- · FAIR data analysis
- · Education & Curriculum Development
- · Antibiotic Resistance Detection

2016-2021 Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam

Ph.D. Candidate

- · Software Development and Pipeline building
- Training Development and Delivery
- · Galaxy System's Administrator
- · Microbiota Analysis and Antibiotic Resistance Detection

2012-2016 Erasmus Medical Center, Rotterdam

Junior Researcher & Bioinformatician

- · Software Development and Pipeline building
- · Galaxy System's Administrator
- · Prostate Cancer Analysis

2010-2012 After's Cool, The Hague Tutor of High School Students.

Tutor of High School Students. Math, Physics, Chemistry

2002-2010 **Self-Employed**

Tutor of High School Students. *Math, Physics, Chemistry*

Projects

2020-2023 Gallantries Project, Coordinator ErasmusMC, Erasmus+ KA203 grant

Continutation of the Gallantries pilot project, development of bioinformatics curricula for higher education and training workshops.

2019-2023 CINECA project Training & Dissemination WP co-lead ErasmusMC,

Horizon2020 grant

CINECA (Common Infrastructure for National Cohorts in Europe, Canada, and Africa) aims at creating a global infrastructure for fedarated data analysis. I Co-lead the Training & Dissemination workpackage, and am also involved in the Healthcare Interoperability & Clinical Applications work package.

2019 Gallantries Pilot Project

ErasmusMC, Mozilla mini-grant

Lesson development combining Galaxy training with Carpentries-style R lessons. Scalable delivery of training via a series of hybrid-style workshops.

2018 Clinical Microbiota Analysis Pipeline

ErasmusMC

Development of a user-friendly analysis pipeline for 16S taxonomic profiling for use in daily clinical diagnostics of patients for Streeklab Haarlem.

Since 2016 GTN: Galaxy Training Materials Infrastructure

GalaxyProject

Co-founder of the GTN infrastructure for the collaborative development of Galaxy training materials. Community building efforts to ensure utility for educators. Development of several tutorials on the topics of Metagenomics, Sequence Analysis, Galaxy Development and Visualisation. https://training.galaxyproject.org

2016 Galaxy CTF

Galaxy Community Conference 2016

Together with Helena Rasche, built a framework and 28 challenges for a "Capture the Flag" event based on Galaxy. Tasks included exploiting recently patched security bugs within Galaxy, Docker security issues, exploring new Galaxy features, and exploiting common bugs in Galaxy tools. Approximately 16 people participated in the competition. The infrastructure for the competition was released afterwards to allow others to re-use it for educational purposes.

Since 2016 Galaxy Interactive Environment Development

GalaxyProject

Created Galaxy Interactive Environments (GIEs) for several applications, including Phinch for metagenomic data visualisation and Ethercalc.

2012-2015 **Prostate Cancer Analysis**

ErasmusMC

Development of analysis tools and workflows for variant analysis in cancer, including fusion gene detection and impact analysis, and identification of somatic variants without normal samples.

Since 2012 Galaxy Tool Development

GalaxyProject

I have integrated over 100 tools into the Galaxy Tool shed, including Complete Genomics Tools, Mothur for 16S rRNA sequence Analysis, Circos for visualisation, and more. Member of Galaxy's IUC team of tool developers that develop and ensure adherance to best-practices and FAIR principles.

Publications

Fostering accessible online education using Galaxy as an e-learning platform

Saskia Hiltemann, Beatriz Serrano-Solano, Patricia M. Palagi, Melanie C. Föll, Cristóbal Gallardo-Alba, Anika Erxleben, Helena Rasche, Saskia Hiltemann, Matthias Fahrner, Mark J. Dunning, Marcel H. Schulz, Beáta Scholtz, Dave Clements, Anton Nekrutenko, Bérénice Batut, and Björn A. Grüning

PLOS Computational Biology (2021). 2021

ASaiM-MT: a validated and optimized ASaiM workflow for metatranscriptomics analysis within Galaxy framework

Subina Mehta, Marie Crane, Emma Leith, Bérénice Batut, Saskia Hiltemann, Magnus Ø Arntzen, Benoit J. Kunath, Phillip B. Pope, Francesco Delogu, Ray Sajulga, Praveen Kumar, James E. Johnson, Timothy J. Griffin, and Pratik D. Jagtap

10 (Apr. 2021) p. 103. F1000 Research Ltd, 2021

Comparison of Illumina versus Nanopore 16S rRNA Gene Sequencing of the Human Nasal Microbiota

Astrid P. Heikema, Deborah Horst-Kreft, Stefan A. Boers, Rick Jansen, Saskia D. Hiltemann, Willem de Koning, Robert Kraaij, Maria A. J. de Ridder, Chantal B. van Houten, Louis J. Bont, Andrew P. Stubbs, and John P. Hays

11.9 (Sept. 2020) p. 1105. MDPI AG, 2020

NanoGalaxy: Nanopore long-read sequencing data analysis in Galaxy

Saskia Hiltemann, Willem de Koning, Milad Miladi, Saskia Hiltemann, Astrid Heikema, John P Hays, Stephan Flemming, Marius van den Beek, Dana A Mustafa, Rolf Backofen, Björn Grüning, and Andrew P Stubbs

GigaScience (2020). 2020

Galactic Circos: User-friendly Circos plots within the Galaxy platform Saskia Hiltemann, Helena Rasche, and Saskia Hiltemann

GigaScience (2020). 2020

Development and evaluation of a culture-free microbiota profiling platform (MYcrobiota) for clinical diagnostics

Stefan A. Boers, Saskia D. Hiltemann, Andrew P. Stubbs, Ruud Jansen, and John P. Hays 37.6 (Mar. 2018) pp. 1081–1089. Springer Science and Business Media LLC, 2018

Galaxy mothur Toolset (GmT): a user-friendly application for 16S rRNA gene sequencing analysis using mothur

Saskia D Hiltemann, Stefan A Boers, Peter J van der Spek, Ruud Jansen, John P Hays, and Andrew P Stubbs

GigaScience (Dec. 2018). Oxford University Press (OUP), 2018

Community-driven data analysis training for biology

Bérénice Batut, Saskia Hiltemann, Andrea Bagnacani, Dannon Baker, Vivek Bhardwaj, Clemens Blank, Anthony Bretaudeau, Loraine Guéguen, Martin Čech, John Chilton, Dave Clements, Olivia Doppelt-Azeroual, Anika Erxleben, Mallory Freeberg, Simon Gladman, Youri Hoogstrate, Hans-Rudolf Hotz, Torsten Houwaart, Pratik Jagtap, Delphine Lariviere, Gildas Le Corguillé, Thomas Manke, Fabien Mareuil, Fidel Ramírez, Devon Ryan, Florian Sigloch, Nicola Soranzo, Joachim Wolff, Pavankumar Videm, Markus Wolfien, Aisanjiang Wubuli, Dilmurat Yusuf, Rolf Backofen, James Taylor, Anton Nekrutenko, and Björn Grüning

(Nov. 2017). Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, 2017

Systematically linking tranSMART, Galaxy and EGA for reusing human translational research data [version 1; referees: 2 approved]

Saskia Hiltemann, Chao Zhang, Jochem Bijlard, Christine Staiger, Serena Scollen, David van Enckevort, Youri Hoogstrate, Alexander Senf, Saskia Hiltemann, Susanna Repo, Wibo Pipping, Mariska Bierkens, Stefan Payralbe, Bas Stringer, Jaap Heringa, Andrew Stubbs, Luiz Olavo Bonino Da Silva Santos, Jeroen Belien, Ward Weistra, Rita Azevedo, Kees van Bochove, Gerrit Meijer, Jan-Willem Boiten, Jordi Rambla, Remond Fijneman, J. Dylan Spalding, and Sanne Abeln

(2017). 2017

Integration of EGA secure data access into Galaxy [version 1; referees: 2 approved] Y Hoogstrate, C Zhang, A Senf, J Bijlard, S Hiltemann, D van Enckevort, S Repo, J Heringa, G Jenster, R J.A. Fijneman, JW Boiten, G A. Meijer, A Stubbs, J Rambla, D Spalding, and S Abeln

F1000Research 5.2841 (2016). 2016

Integration of EGA secure data access into Galaxy

Youri Hoogstrate, Chao Zhang, Alexander Senf, Jochem Bijlard, Saskia Hiltemann, David van Enckevort, Susanna Repo, Jaap Heringa, Guido Jenster, Remond J.A. Fijneman, Jan-Willem Boiten, Gerrit A. Meijer, Andrew Stubbs, Jordi Rambla, Dylan Spalding, and Sanne Abeln

F1000Research 5 (Dec. 2016) p. 2841. F1000 Research, Ltd., 2016

Next-generation sequencing reveals novel rare fusion events with functional implication in prostate cancer

I Teles Alves, Thomas Hartjes, Elizabeth McClellan, Saskia Hiltemann, René Böttcher, Natasja Dits, MR Temanni, Bart Janssen, W Van Workum, Peter van der Spek, et al.

Oncogene 34.5 (2015) pp. 568-577. Nature Publishing Group, 2015

Discriminating somatic and germline mutations in tumor DNA samples without matching normals

Saskia Hiltemann, Guido Jenster, Jan Trapman, Peter van der Spek, and Andrew Stubbs Genome research 25.9 (2015) pp. 1382–1390. Cold Spring Harbor Lab, 2015

FuMa: reporting overlap in RNA-seq detected fusion genes

Youri Hoogstrate, René Böttcher, Saskia Hiltemann, Peter J van der Spek, Guido Jenster, and Andrew P Stubbs

Bioinformatics (2015) btv721. Oxford Univ Press, 2015

iReport: a generalised Galaxy solution for integrated experimental reporting.

Saskia Hiltemann, Youri Hoogstrate, Peter van v. der Spek, Guido Jenster, and Andrew Stubbs

GigaScience 3 (2014). 2014

CGtag: complete genomics toolkit and annotation in a cloud-based Galaxy

Saskia Hiltemann, Hailiang Mei, Mattias de Hollander, Ivo Palli, Peter van der Spek, Guido Jenster, and Andrew Stubbs

GigaScience 3.1 (2014) p. 1. BioMed Central, 2014

ImmunoGlobulin galaxy (IGGalaxy) for simple determination and quantitation of immunoglobulin heavy chain rearrangements from NGS

Michael J Moorhouse, David van Zessen, Hanna IJspeert, Saskia Hiltemann, Sebastian Horsman, Peter J van der Spek, Mirjam van der Burg, and Andrew P Stubbs

BMC immunology 15.1 (2014) p. 59. BioMed Central, 2014

Gene fusions by chromothripsis of chromosome 5q in the VCaP prostate cancer cell line Inês Teles Alves, Saskia Hiltemann, Thomas Hartjes, Peter van der Spek, Andrew Stubbs, Jan Trapman, and Guido Jenster

Human genetics 132.6 (2013) pp. 709-713. Springer, 2013

iFUSE: integrated fusion gene explorer

Saskia Hiltemann, Elizabeth A McClellan, Jos van Nijnatten, Sebastiaan Horsman, Ivo Palli, Ines Teles Alves, Thomas Hartjes, Jan Trapman, Peter van der Spek, Guido Jenster, et al.

Bioinformatics (2013) btt252. Oxford Univ Press, 2013

Huvariome: a web server resource of whole genome next-generation sequencing allelic frequencies to aid in pathological candidate gene selection

Andrew Stubbs, Elizabeth A McClellan, Sebastiaan Horsman, Saskia D Hiltemann, Ivo Palli, Stephan Nouwens, Anton HJ Koning, Frits Hoogland, Joke Reumers, Daphne Heijsman, et al.

Journal of clinical bioinformatics 2.1 (2012) p. 19. BioMed Central, 2012

Multi-coloured Cellular Automata Saskia Hiltemann

Bachelor thesis, Erasmus Universiteit, Rotterdam, Netherlands (2008). 2008